Guide to the Michael Francis Blake photographs, 1912-1934 RL.00119
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Michael Francis Blake photographs
circa 1912-1934
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Blake, Michael Francis, -1934
RL.00119
1.0 Linear Feet 3 boxes 243 items
Michael Francis Blake was one of Charleston, South Carolina's first African American studio photographers. Collection consists of 118 photographs, mostly studio portraits taken by Michael Francis Blake from about 1912 to 1934, with some outdoor settings. There is also a full set of copy prints. The great majority of the subjects appear to be African American; however, there are also individuals who are multi-racial, and possibly white and Asian. Formats comprise 91 photographic postcards and 28 black-and-white prints, many on card mounts but some in the form of more casual snapshots; there are also eight copy negatives. A few of the photographs may be taken by others. Thirty-six individuals in the photographs have been identified, including a portrait of the photographer. Acquired as part of the John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture at Duke University.
Biographical Note
Michael Francis Blake, a graduate of Avery Normal Institute, was one of Charleston, South Carolina's first African American studio photographers. He was born in 1879 on Johns Island, South Carolina, and married Cecelia Ford from Georgetown, S.C. in 1899. Blake moved to Charleston with his family around 1900 and began to work professionally as a photographer in 1912.
Blake had a studio and residence at 12 W. Sumter Street, which later became 384 W. Sumter Street after the street was renumbered in 1918. He also regularly set up his camera on the northwest corner of Radcliffe and King Streets in Charleston. Blake died in Charleston in 1934 at age 55.
Access Restrictions
Original film negatives are closed to use.
Due to the fragility of the original photographs, reference prints or the online digital images are the preferred use format.
Online Items
All original prints from the Michael Blake Francis photographs collection have been digitized and are available on the Duke Digital Collections website.
The Museum of Charleston in Charleston, South Carolina, holds original negatives of many of the prints.
Provenance
The Michael Francis Blake photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1986 and 2020.
Collection Overview
Collection consists of 118 photographs of men, women, and children as single individuals, family groups, and other group shots. There is also a full set of copy prints (preferred for access) and eight copy negatives. The great majority of the subjects appear to be African American; however, there are individuals who are multi-racial, and possibly white and Asian. The photographs were taken by Michael Francis Blake, an African American photographer from Charleston, South Carolina, from about 1912 to 1934, mostly in his studio at 384 West Sumter Street. There are a few that may have been taken by another indiviual. Some of the photographs are stamped with Blake's name and studio addresses.
The majority of the photographs were originally housed in a photograph album entitled "Portraits of Members," also included in the collection, but have been rehoused for preservation purposes. Ninety-one of the photos are photographic postcards and the others are either mounted photographs or snapshots. The predominant style is the formal studio portrait, standing or seated. There are also some informal snapshots that may or may not have been taken by Blake. Some portraits were taken outdoors in front of a backdrop with props such as rugs, chairs and plants to recreate a studio setting. Others were taken on the street; the location of photograph #28 has been identified as just outside of Blake's studio. Some have what appear to be shopping lists and other notations written on the backs, and a few have names, ages, and street addresses, presumably of the sitter or their household.
Through existing captions and public input, thirty-six individuals in the photographs have been identified, including the photographer, Michael Francis Blake, who appears in one portrait.
Each original print has been assigned a unique institutional identifier. All but one have been digitized and are available online through the Duke Digital Collections website.
African American families -- Portraits; African American photographers -- South Carolina -- Charleston; African Americans -- Photographs; African Americans -- Portraits; African Americans -- South Carolina -- Charleston; Asian Americans -- South Carolina -- Charleston -- Portraits; Photography -- South Carolina; Portrait photographers -- South Carolina; Racially mixed people -- South Carolina -- Portraits; Charleston (S.C.) -- History; Charleston (S.C.) -- Social life and customs; South Carolina -- History; Black-and-white photographs; Negatives (photographs); Photograph albums; Photographic postcards; Blake, Michael Francis, -1934
- Original photographs, circa 1912-1934; .25 Linear Feet 1 box 118 prints
  Scope and Contents
  Series consists of one box of 118 original photographic prints, many of them photographic poscards with the rest mounted on cardstock. Most have been are stamped or have been otherwise identified as produced by Michael Francis Blake's photography studio in Charleston, South Carolina. Dates are approximate unless marked on the photograph. In some cases, the studio address reveals the time period. All measurements are in inches.
  Copy prints are available in box 2 and are the preferred format for access to avoid overuse of the originals.
  Additionally, the original prints have been digitized and are available on the Duke Libraries Digital Collections website.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Due to the vulnerability of the original photographs, the modern copy prints or the digital collection images are the preferred format for access.
  - Studio photograph, seated male adult, identified as Michael Francis Blake, circa 1918-1922 (Box 1, Print MFB001)
    3.5 x 5.5. The photographer is unknown, or it may have been taken by Blake with a remote shutter release.
  - Snapshot, female adult standing by an automobile, unidentified, undated, 3.25 x 5.5 (Box 1, Print MFB002)
  - Studio photograph, standing female adult holding a book, unidentified, circa 1926-1934, 3.5 x 5.5. Embossed with Blake's studio address. (Box 1, Print MFB003)
  - Studio photograph, female adult, identified as Lillie Ford, 4 August 1926, 3.5 x 5.5. Writing on photograph: "Lillie Ford taken Aug 4 1926" (Box 1, Print MFB004)
  - Studio photograph, standing male child, unidentified, circa 1918-1922, 3.5 x 5.5 (Box 1, Print MFB005)
  - Studio photograph, standing female adult holding a basket of flowers, identified as Francis Smalls, circa 1918-1922, 3.5 x 5.5. Writing on photograph: "Frances Smalls / my niece Frances / Georgetown S.C." (Box 1, Print MFB006)
  - Snapshot, male child, unidentified, undated, 3 x 4.5. Writing on photograph: "To my dear Aunt Rosa your Nephew Edwin." Stamped "469". (Box 1, Print MFB007)
  - Studio photograph, standing young male adult, unidentified, undated, 3.5 x 5.5 (Box 1, Print MFB008)
  - Snapshot, male adult standing by a porch, identified as "Frederick," undated, 2.75 x 4.25. Writing on photograph: "Frederick" (Box 1, Print MFB009)
  - Studio photograph, standing male adult and female adult, unidentified, circa 1912-1918, 3.5 x 5.5 (Box 1, Print MFB010)
  - Studio photograph, seated male adult, identified as Jesse E. Beard, a pastor of Morris Brown AME Church and vice president of the People's Federal Bank in Charleston, S.C., circa 1910s, 3.5 x 5.5. Embossed with Blake's studio address. (Box 1, Print MFB011)
  - Studio photograph, standing child, unidentified, circa 1918-1922, 3.5 x 5.5 (Box 1, Print MFB012)
  - Studio photograph, seated infant propped up on a chair, unidentified, 1933 June 29, 3.5 x 5.5. Writing on photograph: "Taken Thursday 29/33 - June Age 3 months." Embossed with Blake's studio address. (Box 1, Print MFB013)
  - Studio photograph, male adult, unidentified, circa 1912-1918, 3.5 x 5.5. Stamped with Blake's studio address: "M.F. Blake View Photographer 12 W. Sumter Street. Phone 1341-L, Charleston, S.C." (Box 1, Print MFB014)
  - Studio photograph, seated female adult, unidentified, circa 1912-1918, 3.5 x 5.5 (Box 1, Print MFB015)
  - Studio photograph, child standing on a chair and an infant seated on a chair, identified as Bennie children, circa 1926-1934, 3.5 x 5.5. Embossed with Blake's studio address. (Box 1, Print MFB016)
  - Studio photograph, seated male adult and a standing female adult with her arm around his shoulders, unidentified, circa 1926-1934, 3.5 x 5.5 (Box 1, Print MFB017)
  - Studio photograph, seated elderly male adult, identified as James W. White, circa 1918-1922, 3.5 x 5.5. Stamped with Blake's studio address: "M. Blake Night and Day Photographer 384 W. Sumter Street, Charleston, S.C." (Box 1, Print MFB018)
  - Studio photograph, standing male adult, identified as Philips Michael Smalls, circa 1912-1918, 3.5 x 5.5 (Box 1, Print MFB019)
  - Studio photograph, male child standing on a chair, unidentified, circa 1926-1934, 3.5 x 5.5. Embossed with Blake's studio address. (Box 1, Print MFB020)
  - Studio photograph, male adult, identified as E. H. Coit, circa 1912, 3.5 x 5.5. This man appears in several other portraits. E.H. Coit is listed as a "mulatto preacher" born about 1860 in the 1910 Federal census. He may have been about 50 in this photograph. (Box 1, Print MFB021)
  - Studio photograph, male child standing on a chair, unidentified, circa 1926-1934, 3.5 x 5.5. Embossed with Blake's studio address. Duplicate of image MFB020. (Box 1, Print MFB022)
  - Studio photograph, seated male adult and a standing female adult with her arm around his shoulders, "Bennie and wife," circa 1926-1934, 3.5 x 5.5. Writing on photograph: "Bennie and wife." Embossed with Blake's studio address at 384 W. Sumter Street. (Box 1, Print MFB023)
  - Studio photograph, seated male adult, identified as Eddie Ford, 1932 June 10, 3.5 x 5.5. Writing on photograph: "Eddie Ford. Taken June 10th 1932." Embossed with Blake's studio address at 384 W. Sumter Street. (Box 1, Print MFB024)
  - Studio photograph, standing female child holding a flower, unidentified, circa 1912-1918, 3.5 x 5.5 (Box 1, Print MFB025)
  - Studio photograph, standing female adult wearing a hat and a coat, identified as D. F. Murray, circa 1918-1922, 3.5 x 5.5. Writing on photograph: "D.F. Murray, Sumter St., Columbia SC." Stamped with Blake's studio address: "M. Blake Night and Day Photographer, 384 W. Sumter Street, Charleston, S.C." Negative on file. (Box 1, Print MFB026)
  - Snapshot, two female adults sitting on the front porch of a house, unidentified, undated, 3.5 x 2.75. Stamped on verso "10011". (Box 1, Print MFB027)
  - Snapshot, female adult standing and holding an infant at street address 384, identified possibly as Mrs. Blake, undated, 2.5 x 4.5. The location's address number, 384, visible on a brick wall to the left of the subject, is the same as Blake's studio address. A lower portion of the border is missing. (Box 1, Print MFB028)
  - Studio photograph, female adult, identified as Irene Green, circa 1926-1934, 3.5 x 5.5. Writing on photograph: "Johns Island SC. Mrs. Irene Green." Same woman as in MFB004 but identified with a different name. (Box 1, Print MFB029)
  - Studio photograph, standing female adult, unidentified, circa 1912-1918, 3.5 x 5.5 (Box 1, Print MFB030)
  - Studio photograph, seated child, identified as Leon Ignatius Ford, Jr., circa 1921, 3.5 x 5.5. Writing on photograph: "Leon Ignatius Ford Jr. 1 yr 2 wks." (Box 1, Print MFB031)
  - Outdoor portrait, female adult standing on a path, unidentified, circa 1918-1922, 3.5 x 5.5 (Box 1, Print MFB032)
  - Studio photograph, standing female adult, unidentified, circa 1912-1918, 3.5 x 5.5 (Box 1, Print MFB033)
  - Studio photograph, seated female adult, identified as Helen Ford, circa 1918-1922, 3.5 x 5.5. Writing on photograph: "Mrs. Helen Ford." Stamped with Blake's studio address: "M. Blake Night and Day Photographer 384 W. Sumter Street, Charleston, S.C." (Box 1, Print MFB034)
  - Snapshot, dog lying down on ground, undated, 3 x 4.5 (Box 1, Print MFB035)
  - Studio photograph, standing female adult, unidentified, circa 1918-1922, 3.5 x 5.5 (Box 1, Print MFB036)
  - Studio photograph, seated male adult, unidentified, circa 1912-1918, 3.5 x 5.5. Stamped with Blake's studio address: "M.F. Blake View Photographer 12 W. Sumter Street. Phone 1341-L, Charleston, S.C." (Box 1, Print MFB037)
  - Studio photograph, female child and standing female adult with her arm around the shoulders of an older seated female adult, unidentified, circa 1926-1934, 3.5 x 5.5. Embossed with Blake's studio address at 384 W. Sumter Street. (Box 1, Print MFB038)
  - Studio photograph, seated male adult, identified as Eddie Ford, circa 1918-1922, 3.5 x 5.5. Stamped with Blake's studio address: "M.F. Blake View Photographer 384 W. Sumter Street Charleston, S.C." (Box 1, Print MFB039)
  - Studio photograph, two standing female adults, unidentified, circa 1912-1915, 3.5 x 5.5 (Box 1, Print MFB040)
  - Studio photograph, female adult, unidentified, undated, 1.375 x 1.75 (Box 1, Print MFB041)
  - Studio photograph, two standing female young adults leaning on older male child, unidentified, circa 1918-1922, 3.5 x 5.5. Stamped with Blake's studio address: " M. Blake Night and Day Photographer 384 W. Sumter Street, Charleston, S.C." (Box 1, Print MFB042)
  - Studio photograph, standing female adult, unidentified, circa 1918-1922, 3.5 x 5.5. Stamped with Blake's studio address: "M. Blake Night and Day Photographer 384 W. Sumter Street, Charleston, S.C." (Box 1, Print MFB043)
  - Studio photograph, standing male child dressed in formal wear, unidentified, circa 1918-1922, 3.5 x 5.5 (Box 1, Print MFB044)
  - Studio photograph, seated child, unidentified, undated, 3.25 x 5 (Box 1, Print MFB045)
  - Studio photograph, male adult standing by a door, unidentified, circa 1918-1922, 3.5 x 5.5. Stamped with Blake's studio address: "M.F. Blake, 384 W. Sumter Street, View Photographer, Phone 1341-W, Charleston, S.C." (Box 1, Print MFB046)
  - Studio photograph, standing male child, unidentified, circa 1918-1922, 3.5 x 5.5. Stamped with Blake's studio address: "M.F. Blake, 384 W. Sumter Street, View Photographer Phone 1341-W, Charleston, S.C." (Box 1, Print MFB047)
  - Studio photograph, seated infant, unidentified, undated, 3.5 x 5.5 (Box 1, Print MFB048)
  - Studio photograph, standing female adult, unidentified, circa 1912-1918, 3.5 x 5.5 (Box 1, Print MFB049)
  - Studio photograph, seated female adult, unidentified, circa 1918-1922, 3.5 x 5.5. Embossed with Blake's studio address at 384 W. Sumter Street. (Box 1, Print MFB050)
  - Studio photograph, infant posed on a bench, unidentified, circa 1926-1934, 3.5 x 5.5. Embossed with Blake's studio address at 384 W. Sumter Street. (Box 1, Print MFB051)
  - Studio photograph, seated male adult, Jesse E. Beard, pastor and banker, circa 1910s, 3.5 x 5.5. Same photograph as MFB011, identified as Jesse E. Beard, a pastor of Morris Brown AME Church and vice president of the People's Federal Bank in Charleston, S.C. (Box 1, Print MFB052)
  - Studio photograph, standing young female, identified as Jessie Rodrigues, circa 1918-1922, 3.5 x 5.5. Stamped with Blake's studio address: "M.F. Blake, Night and Day Photographer, 384 W. Sumter Street, Charleston, S.C." (Box 1, Print MFB053)
    Jessie Rodrigues and older members of her family, also located in another Blake photograph, are listed as "mulatto" in the 1880, 1910 and 1920 Federal Censuses; in the 1930 and 1940 censuses, the family appears as "Negro (Black)."
  - Studio photograph, standing female adult, unidentified, circa 1912-1918, 3.5 x 5.5 (Box 1, Print MFB054)
  - Studio photograph, female adult, identified as Lucy Meyers, circa 1912-1918, 3.5 x 5.5. Writing on photograph: "Mrs. Lucy Meyers". (Box 1, Print MFB055)
  - Studio photograph, seated elderly male adult, identified as Sandy Simmons, circa 1926-1934, 3.5 x 5.5. Embossed with Blake's studio address. (Box 1, Print MFB056)
  - Studio photograph, child standing on a chair and an infant seated on a chair, identified as Bennie children, circa 1926-1934, 3.5 x 5.5. Writing on photograph: "Bennie Children". Embossed with Blake's studio address. (Box 1, Print MFB057)
  - Studio photograph, seated male adult, identified as J. Donovan Moore, a music teacher, circa 1926-1939, 3.5 x 5.5. Embossed with Blake's studio address at 384 W. Sumter Street. (Box 1, Print MFB058)
  - Studio photograph, male adult, unidentified, circa 1926-1934, 3.5 x 5.5 (Box 1, Print MFB059)
  - Studio photograph, male adult, unidentified, circa 1918-1922, 3.5 x 5.5 (Box 1, Print MFB060)
  - Studio photograph, standing male adult in formal wear, unidentified, undated, 3.25 x 5 (Box 1, Print MFB061)
  - Studio photograph, male adult standing next to female adult who is wearing pants and holding a cigar, identified as Olivia Edith Garrett Wilson and Gustavius Sinkler Wilson, circa 1910-1922, 3.5 x 5.5 (Box 1, Print MFB062)
  - Outdoor photograph, adult male sitting on a chair, identified as M.A. Hollins, circa 1918-1922, 3.5 x 5.5. Embossed with Blake's studio address at 384 W. Sumter Street. (Box 1, Print MFB063)
  - Snapshot, standing female adult and four younger females, identified as Allane Rodrigues, Henrietta Jones Rodrigues, Daisy Rodrigues, Dorothy, Hortense, circa 1930, 3.75 x 3. Embossed with Blake's studio address. (Box 1, Print MFB064)
    The family of Henry and Henrietta Rodrigues, whose daughter Jessie is also the subject of another Blake photograph, is listed as "mulatto" in the 1880, 1910 and 1920 Federal Censuses; in the 1930 and 1940 censuses, they appear as "Negro (Black)."
  - Snapshot, standing female adult and four younger females, identified as Allane Rodrigues, Henrietta Jones Rodrigues, Daisy Rodrigues, Dorothy, Hortense, circa 1930, 3.75 x 3. Embossed with Blake's studio address. Same photograph as MFB064. (Box 1, Print MFB065)
  - Studio photograph, male adult, unidentified, circa 1918-1922, 3.5 x 5.5 (Box 1, Print MFB066)
  - Studio photograph, five standing children, unidentified, circa 1910-1918, 3.5 x 5.5. Stamped with Blake's studio address: "M.F. Blake View Photographer 12 W. Sumter Street. Phone 1341-L, Charleston, S.C." Negative on file. (Box 1, Print MFB067)
  - Studio photograph, standing female adult, unidentified, circa 1926-1939, 3.5 x 5.5. Embossed with Blake's studio address at 384 W. Sumter Street. (Box 1, Print MFB068)
  - Studio photograph, male adult, identified as John McQueen, circa 1926-1939, 3.5 x 5.5. Writing on photograph: "John McQueen". (Box 1, Print MFB069)
  - Studio photograph, male adult, identified as Jesse E. Beard, a pastor of Morris Brown AME Church and vice president of the People's Federal Bank in Charleston, S.C., circa 1926-1934, 3.5 x 5.5. Embossed with Blake's studio address at 384 W. Sumter. Same photograph as MFB011 and MFB052. (Box 1, Print MFB070)
  - Studio photograph, female adult, identified as Olivia Edith Garrett Wilson, circa 1926-1934, 3.5 x 5.5. Writing on photograph: "Ollsey Garett". Photograph of a small nearly square photograph of a stylishly dressed woman, approximately 1.5 x 1 inch, placed on top of a larger mount with oval. Identified as by Blake, 384 W. Sumter. (Box 1, Print MFB071)
  - Studio photograph, female adult, unidentified, circa 1918-1922, 3.5 x 5.5 (Box 1, Print MFB072)
  - Studio photograph, seated female adult, unidentified, circa 1918-1922, 3.5 x 5.5 (Box 1, Print MFB073)
  - Studio photograph, seated female adult, unidentified, circa 1910-1918, 3.5 x 5.5 (Box 1, Print MFB074)
  - Studio photograph, seated female adult using a telephone as a prop, unidentified, circa 1926-1934, 3.5 x 5.5. Embossed with Blake's studio address at 384 W. Sumter. Two negatives on file. (Box 1, Print MFB075)
  - Studio photograph, two seated adult males playing checkers at a table outdoors and four adult males standing behind them, unidentified, circa 1913-1922, 3.5 x 5.5. Negative on file. (Box 1, Print MFB076)
  - Studio photograph, male adult, identified as Isaiah Nathaniel Aiken, 1922 April 23; 3.5 x 5.5. Writing on photograph: "Sunday April 23 1922". (Box 1, Print MFB077)
  - Studio photograph, standing male adult, unidentified, circa 1910-1918, 3.5 x 5.5 (Box 1, Print MFB078)
  - Outdoor photograph, seated elderly female adult holding a small dog, standing child and two standing female adults, unidentified, circa 1910-1918, 3.5 x 5.5. Negative on file. (Box 1, Print MFB079)
  - Studio photograph, seated female adult with two children, identified as Anna Beatrice Aiken, Isaiah Nathaniel Aiken, Jr., Arthur Aiken, circa 1918-1922, 3.5 x 5.5 (Box 1, Print MFB080)
  - Studio photograph, standing female adult, unidentified, circa 1910-1918, 3.5 x 5.5. Same photograph as MFB030. (Box 1, Print MFB081)
  - Studio photograph, seated female adult, unidentified, circa 1910-1918, 3.5 x 5.5 (Box 1, Print MFB082)
  - Studio photograph, two male adults, unidentified, circa 1918-1922, 3.5 x 5.5. Stamped with Blake's studio address: "M.F. Blake, Night and Day Photographer, 384 W. Sumter Street, Charleston, S.C." (Box 1, Print MFB083)
  - Outdoor photograph, portrait of standing female adult, unidentified, circa 1918-1922, 3.5 x 5.5 (Box 1, Print MFB084)
  - Studio photograph, standing female adult and standing male adult, unidentified, circa 1910-1918, 3.5 x 5.5 (Box 1, Print MFB085)
  - Studio photograph, standing female young adult with her arm around seated male young adult, unidentified, circa 1926-1939, 3.5 x 5.5. Embossed with Blake's studio address at 384 W. Sumter Street. (Box 1, Print MFB086)
  - Studio photograph, female adult, unidentified, 20 February 1925, 3.5 x 5.5. Writing on photograph: "Feb. 20th day 1925". Stamped with Blake's studio address: "M.F. Blake View Photographer 384 W. Sumter Street Charleston, S.C." (Box 1, Print MFB087)
  - Studio photograph, standing female child next to a doll seated on a chair, unidentified, circa 1918-1922, 3.5 x 5.5. Embossed with Blake's studio address. Negative on file. (Box 1, Print MFB088)
  - Studio photograph, seated male adult, unidentified, circa 1926-1934, 3.5 x 5.5. Embossed with Blake's 384 W. Sumter studio address. (Box 1, Print MFB089)
  - Outdoor photograph, elderly man standing by a screen door or window, holding an open book, unidentified, circa 1918-1922, 3.5 x 5.5. Stamped with Blake's studio address: "M.F. Blake, Night and Day Photographer, 384 W. Sumter Street, Charleston, S.C." (Box 1, Print MFB090)
  - Studio photograph, elderly man standing by a tall stool with a hat on it, holding a book, identified as Rev. Lowry Alston, circa 1918-1922, 3.5 x 5.5. Writing on photograph: "Rev. Lowry Alston - #413 - Orange St. Georgetown S.C." Stamped with Blake's studio address: "M.F. Blake, Night and Day Photographer, 384 W. Sumter Street, Charleston, S.C." Negative on file. (Box 1, Print MFB091)
  - Studio photograph, standing adult female and standing adult male on either side of a seated child in a chair, unidentified, circa 1918-1922, 3.5 x 5.5 (Box 1, Print MFB092)
  - Studio photograph, standing child, unidentified, circa 1910-1918, 3.25 x 5.25 (Box 1, Print MFB093)
  - Studio photograph, standing child, unidentified, circa 1910-1918, 3.25 x 5.25 (Box 1, Print MFB094)
  - Studio photograph, standing female adult holding a book, unidentified, circa 1926-1934, 3.5 x 5.5. Embossed with Blake's studio address. Same photograph as MFB003. (Box 1, Print MFB095)